{
  "version": 2.0,
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "1. Which of the following method is commonly used for separation of DNA by electrophoresis? ",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Agarose- horizontal",
        "b": "PAGE- vertical",
        "c": "Agarose- vertical",
        "d": "PAGE- horizontal"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. What is the criterion for the movement of DNA fragments on agarose gel during gel electrophoresis?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "The larger the fragment size, the farther it moves",
        "b": "The smaller the fragment size, the farther it moves",
        "c": "Positively charged fragments move to farther end",
        "d": "Negatively charged fragments do not move"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "b",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. For the preparation of agarose gel in electrophoresis, agarose is dissolved in",
      "answers": {
        "a": "TAE buffer",
        "b": "Distilled water",
        "c": "Oil based emulsion",
        "d": "Alcohol"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. What applications can gel electrophoresis be used for?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Parental Testing",
        "b": "Criminal Investigations",
        "c": "Comparing relationships of species",
        "d": "All of the above"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The separated DNA fragments can be visualized after staining with _____, followed by exposure with _____.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "β-galactosidase, gamma radiation",
        "b": "Ethidium bromide, UV radiation",
        "c": "β-galactosidase, UV radiation",
        "d": "Ethidium bromide, gamma radiation"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "b",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. The type and density of the gel are important because",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Some DNA nucleotides may be lost due to chemical reactions with the gel ",
        "b": "They may cause some DNA molecules to replicate",
        "c": "They influence the rate of migration of the fragments ",
        "d": "Some DNA molecules may sink to the bottom and not migrate"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Identify the correct sequence of events of agarose gel electrophoresis.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Gel preparation → casting the gel → forming wells using comb → cooling the gel → removing comb → loading sample in the wells → turning on power → eluting band to get gene of interest",
        "b": "Gel preparation → casting the gel → cooling the gel → inserting combs into well → removing comb → turning on power → loading sample in the wells → eluting band to get gene of interest",
        "c": "Gel preparation → casting the gel → cooling the gel → inserting combs into well → removing comb → loading sample in the wells → turning on power → eluting band to get gene of interest",
        "d": "Gel preparation → casting the gel → cooling the gel → inserting combs into well → loading sample in the wells → removing comb → turning on power → eluting band to get gene of interest"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Why do the fragments of DNA in gel electrophoresis travel away from the negative electrode?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "DNA is negatively charged so is attracted to the positive end of the unit",
        "b": "DNA is positively charged so is attracted to the negative end of the unit",
        "c": "The agarose gel is negatively charged",
        "d": "The agarose gel is positively charged"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. The electrophoresis apparatus consists of:",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Electrophoresis unit and DNA separator",
        "b": "Gel, power pack and buffer chamber",
        "c": "Electrophoresis unit and buffer chamber",
        "d": "Power pack and Electrophoresis unit"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What is the purpose of loading a DNA ladder in agarose gel electrophoresis?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "To measure the size of DNA molecules",
        "b": "To provide a reference for estimating migration distance",
        "c": "To separate the DNA molecules",
        "d": "To determine the charge of DNA molecules"
      },
      
      "correctAnswer": "b",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    }
  ]
}
